Finding Aid for Nabeel Abraham papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Lectures and Presentations
  The Lectures and Presentations series (1.5 linear feet) contains materials, including lecture notes, flyers, and background materials, detailing some of the many lectures and talks given by Abraham in a diverse array of forums, including universities, conferences, schools, and churches. Many of the talks reflect Abraham's criticism of U.S. policy in the Middle East and Israeli policy with regard to Lebanon and the Palestinians. He participated in several teach-ins demonstrating against U.S. involvement in the Gulf War and the invasion of Iraq in 2003. Of note is a 1990 lecture on Salmon Rushdie's The Satanic Verses, which was disrupted by members of the audience but nonetheless finished by Abraham.
  - Arab History: ACCESS (Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services), 1998-1999 (Box 22)
  - "Arab-Americans: Past and Present,", 1980 (Box 22)
  - Arab-Israel-Seaholm High School, 1991 (Box 22)
  - Arabs in America, 1974-1987; undated (Box 22)
  - Beit Hanina Convention, 1988 (Box 22)
  - Beit Sahour, undated (Box 22)
  - Buffalo, 1993 (Box 22)
  - "Consequences of the Gulf War for the Arabs and Arab-Americans,", 1991 (Box 22)
  - Culture and Stasis, 1987 (Box 22)
  - "Discrimination of Jews by Jews: the Case of the Oriental Jew,", undated (Box 22)
  - Great Decisions, 1990 (Box 22)
  - Gulf Crisis: Background, 1990-1991 (Box 22)
  - Happiness, 2000-2003 (Box 22)
  - HFCC (Henry Ford Community College)
    - Cultural Task Force Seminar, 1992 (Box 22)
    - "Poetry and Prose on the War,", 2003 (Box 22)
  - "An Historical Overview of the Current Conflict in the Middle East: a Palestinian Perspective,", undated (Box 22)
  - Illusion of Peace, 1993 (Box 22)
  - Introductions, 1985-1991 (Box 22)
  - "Iraq-Israel-Palestine-U.S.: the Middle East at the Crossroads,", 2003 (Box 22)
  - Iraq Talk, 2002 (Box 22)
  - "Israel, the Palestinians and the Gulf War,", 1991 (Box 22)
  - Lay Academy of Religion, Wooster College: "The Agony of the Palestinians,", 1991 (Box 22)
  - Lebanon Crisis, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Lecture Notices, 1985-2001; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Macomb Community College, 1990 (Box 22)
  - Media Talk, 2000-2001 (Box 22)
  - Middle East Conflict, undated (Box 22)
  - "The Middle East: Myth and Reality"-Midland Schools/ Monroe Public Library, 1989-1990 (Box 22)
  - Models for Reconciliation,", 1988 (Box 22)
  - MSU (Michigan State University): "Terrorists, Fundamentalists, and Media Pundits,", undated (Box 22)
  - OAH (Organization of American Historians), 2001-2002 (Box 22)
  - "Palestine Since the Handshake,", 1995 (Box 22)
  - Palestinian Case Lecture, 1983-1985 (Box 22)
  - Peace Coalition Forum on Middle East, 1990 (Box 22)
  - "Peoples and Cultures of the Middle East,", 1990 (Box 22)
  - PLO (Palestine Liberation Organization) Peace Initiative, undated (Box 22)
  - "The Politics of Heresy: The Satanic Verses Revisited,", 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 22)
  - "Prospects for Peace in Lebanon and the Middle East,", 1981-1984 (Box 23)
  - "Reflections on the Gulf War,", 1991 (Box 23)
  - "Rethinking Palestine,", undated (Box 23)
  - Rise of Palestinian Nationalism, 1994 (Box 23)
  - Saline Unitarian Church, 2003 (Box 23)
  - Sinbad, 1975-1996; undated (Box 23)
  - "Stereotypes as a Reflection of Self: the Middle East through American Eyes" (LAND (Liberal Arts Network for Development) Conference), 1991-1992 (Box 23)
  - Teach-Ins, 1990-1992 (Box 23)
  - Schoolcraft Community College, 1972 (Box 23)
  - University of Michigan
    - 9/11 Panel, 2001 (Box 23)
    - Dearborn
      - "The Palestinian Nationalist Movement: Fifty Years of Turbulence,", 1976 (Box 23)
      - Peace Prospects, 1981-1990 (Box 23)
    - Flint, 1992 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-1976; undated; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - OAS (Organization of Arab Students) Education Seminar, 1973 (Box 23)
    - Teach-In, 1990-1991 (Box 23)
  - University of South Florida, 1976 (Box 23)
  - U.S. Interests in Middle East, 1985-1994 (Box 23)
  - "Writing as a Way of Life,", 1979-2004 (Box 23)
  - Wayne State University
    - Media Lecture, 1991-1993 (Box 23)
    - "The Palestine Problem: an Historical Perspective,", 1976 (Box 23)
  - Yom Kippur War, 1973-1974; undated (Box 23)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series (2 linear feet) includes newspapers, newsletters, bulletins, pamphlets, and event programs collected by Abraham from various organizations focused on Arab Americans or Middle East issues. Some of the more prominent organizations represented here include the Association of Arab-American University Graduates (AAUG), Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services (ACCESS), American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), and Organization of Arab Students (OAS). Some of these materials are in Arabic.
  - AACAC (Arab American Community Advisory Council)-Al-Jaliyah, 1979 (Box 23)
  - AACP (Arab American Congress for Palestine), 1971 (Box 23)
  - AAPAC (American Arab Political Action Committee), 2002-2004 (Box 23)
  - AAUG (Association of Arab-American University Graduates)
    - Annual Conventions, 1979-1982 (Box 23)
    - "The First Decade,", 1977 (Box 23)
    - Information Papers, 1973-1975 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1977 (Box 23)
    - Newsletters, 1973-1979 (Box 23)
  - ACCESS (Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services), 1975-2002; undated; 2 folders (Box 23)
  - ADC (American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee)
    - ADC Reports, 1980-1983 (Box 23)
    - "The Arab Image in American Film and Television,", undated (Box 23)
    - Background/Issue Papers, 1983-1990; undated (Box 23)
    - Detroit Regional Office Newsletters, 1983-1984 (Box 23)
    - National Conventions, 2000-2002 (Box 23)
    - Updates on the Situation in Lebanon, 1982 (Box 23)
    - "Wrapping the Grapeleaves: A Sheaf of Contemporary Arab-American Poets,", 1982 (Box 23)
  - AHSWC (Arab Human Services Workers Coalition)-Human Service Directory, Arab Community-Metro Detroit, 1982-1983 (Box 24)
  - AIYS (American Institute for Yemeni Studies)-AIYS Newsletter, 1983 (Box 24)
  - Arab American News (Sada al-Watan), 1991; 2002 (Box 24)
  - Arab World Festival Program Book, 1986 (Box 24)
  - Arabic Language Materials (Miscellaneous) (Box 24)
  - Arrafideyn, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Detroit Free Press-"100 Questions and Answers About Arab Americans,", 2000 (Box 24)
  - Ethnic Heritage Studies Program, Center for Urban Studies, Wayne State University-"America's Immigrants: Arabs in the New World,"1983 (Box 24)
  - FIA (Federation of Islamic Associations), undated (Box 24)
  - Filastinuna...Our Palestine, 1981 (Box 24)
  - MENA (Middle Eastern and North African) Film Festival, 2002 (Box 24)
  - MEOC (Middle East Outreach Council) Newsletter, 1981-1983 (Box 24)
  - MERA Forum (Forum for Middle East Research in Anthropology), 1982-1983 (Box 24)
  - MERIP (Middle East Research and Information Project)-Middle East Report, 1989-1990 (Box 24)
  - MESA (Middle East Studies Association), 1980-1984 (Box 24)
  - Nahnu, circa 1975-1976 (Box 24)
  - Najda Newsletter, 1983 (Box 24)
  - OAS (Organization of Arab Students)
    - Al-Masira, circa, 1977-1982; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Information Guides, 1975-1977 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-1981 (Box 25)
    - Studies, 1974 (Box 25)
  - PAS (Palestine Aid Society), 1982; 2002 (Box 25)
  - Programs (Miscellaneous), 1981-2005 (Box 25)
  - Sawt Alahrar, 1980 (Box 25)
  - SEDCC (Southeast Dearborn Community Council, Inc.) News, 1983 (Box 25)
  - Your Community Voice (Al-As-Hab), 2004 (Box 25)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual series (1.5 linear feet) consists of debates, interviews, and talks on VHS tape, cassette tape, and CD. Some of these feature Abraham, while some involve others such as Noam Chomsky, Abdeen Jabara, and Edward Said.
  - VHS Tapes
    - ABC News-Detroit Arab Community, 1990 (Box 25)
    - Aquinas College, 2000 (Box 25)
    - Chomsky, Noam-"The Middle East: War, Peace and the Media,", 1991 (Box 25)
    - Christopher Columbus, 2002 (Box 25)
    - Detroit Historical Museum/CNN Ramadan Convention Coverage, 1997-1998 (Box 25)
    - Focus-Arab Detroit Book, 2000 (Box 25)
    - Forum on the Middle East "Will there Ever be Peace?", 2000 (Box 25)
    - In America "The Arab-American Story" (International Channel), 2003 (Box 25)
    - "Living in America: Identity and Immigration" (UM Flint), 1992 (Box 25)
    - McNeil-Lehrer-Karima at UM, 1990 (Box 25)
    - News Recordings, 1985-1991 (Box 25)
    - "The Politics of Heresy: The Satanic Verses Revisited,", 1990 (Box 25)
    - "The Satanic Verses: Literature or Heresy?", 1989 (Box 25)
    - "In Search of Community: Reflections on a 25 Year Journey,", 1995 (Box 25)
    - "Second Look,", 1988 (Box 25)
    - Shryock, Andrew-"Flourishing on the Margins: A Community Portrait of Arab Americans,", 1998 (Box 25)
    - Sister Najjah, undated (Box 25)
  - Cassette Tapes (Box 26)
    - 25 Years of Occupation, 1992; 2 tapes (Box 26)
    - All Things Considered
      - 1982, 2 tapes (Box 26)
      - Interview, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Amer, Ron-Interview, 1998 (Box 26)
    - Arabesque: Human Rights (Edward Said, Noam Chomsky, et al.), 1989 (Box 26)
    - Bassam, Tibi-Lecture, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Chomsky, Noam
      - Interviews
        - Arabesque Radio (by Michael Dalton and Warren David), 1984 (Box 26)
        - On Human Rights, 1988 (Box 26)
        - Untitled, 1984 (Box 26)
      - Lecture, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Cockburn, Alexander (ADC Banquet), 1982 (Box 26)
    - "Dialogue Detroit"
      - 1988 (Box 26)
      - 1991 (Box 26)
    - Finkelstein, Norm, 1996 (Box 26)
    - Hassan, Jaber-Interview, 1998; 2 tapes (Box 26)
    - Imam Qazwini, Islamic Center of Detroit-Interview, 2002 (Box 26)
    - Jabara, Abdeen
      - Debate, circa 1988 (Box 26)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 26)
    - Middle East Conference, UM Ann Arbor (Dennis Brutus, Abdeen Jabara, Sameer Abraham), circa 1978 (Box 26)
    - "Over a Cup of Tea," Arab-American Media Society (Sameer Abraham, Nabeel Abraham, Warren David), 1985 (Box 26)
    - Panel Discussion, 1973 (Box 26)
    - Said, Edward
      - ADC, 1987 (Box 26)
      - "Demonization of Islam,", 1995 (Box 26)
      - NPR, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Shahak, Israel, undated (Box 26)
    - Shryock, Andrew-A Community Portrait of Arab Americans, 1998 (Box 26)
    - WXYT Radio, 1990 (Box 26)
  - CD
    - Arab Americans After 9/11 (Michigan Radio), circa 2000 (Box 26)